<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Some considerations relating to the trade to Guiny</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 5 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60784</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S4494C</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R218720</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99830291</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99830291</idno>
            <idno type="VID">34741</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60784)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 34741)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2020:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Some considerations relating to the trade to Guiny</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([2] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original at the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Trading companies --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Commerce --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:34741:1"/>
            <head>SOME CONSIDERATIONS Relating to the Trade to Guiny.</head>
            <p>THE <hi>Royal Company,</hi> as they call themſelves, are a great In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury to the Nation in divers Reſpects.</p>
            <p n="1">I. They hinder the vent of the Woollen Manufacture, trading themſelves inconſiderably, nor ſuffering others, whereby not a Tenth part of the Product of <hi>England</hi> is Exported for <hi>Guiny,</hi> as might be, if the Trade were open, or managed by a Regulated Company.</p>
            <p n="2">II. They occaſion the Decay of Navigation; Ten times the Number of Seamen and Ships might be imployed in that Trade, were it open, or regulated as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p n="3">III. They Advance the Intereſt and Trade of other Nations; for whilſt we forbear to ſupply that Coaſt with Goods, other Nations fill it, and beat us out of our Trade with their Manufactures, when our own would at the ſame time vend better amongſt the Natives, if we would ſupply the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. They are dangerous for the reſt of their Majeſties Subjects to deal with; for when a Company has a mind (after they have made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Dividends) they may break, thô every Individual Perſon be very rich, there is no Remedy for the Creditors.</p>
            <p n="5">V. They ſet what Price they pleaſe upon the Manufacture of <hi>England,</hi> ſo lower the Price of Wool, ruin the Workers and Dealers in the Woollen Manufacture, becauſe there is but one Buyer.</p>
            <p n="6">VI. They ſet what Price they pleaſe on Ships they hire, for they have none of their own, and ſo Diſcourage the Building of Ships, as well as Maſters and Seamen.</p>
            <p n="7">VII. They conſequently hinder their Majeſties Cuſtoms.</p>
            <p n="8">VIII. They have heretofore (and therefore may be expected from them again) been the great Invaders of Property, and contrary to Law and Juſtice, have taken from their Fellow Subjects their Ships and Goods, and granted Commiſſions ſo to do; and in all Differences with thoſe they deal with, have been Judges in their own Caſes.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:34741:2"/>
            <p n="11">XI. They hinder all manner of Diſcoveries of Places; and that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Ingenious Men would go upon, were it not that this Company will let none Profit thereby but themſelves.</p>
            <p n="10">X. They ruin their Majeſties Plantations;
<list>
                  <item>1. By their not Supplying them with the quantity of Negroes ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary.</item>
                  <item>2. By taking Exceſſive Rates for thoſe they ſell.</item>
                  <item>3. By furniſhing them with Negroes unfit.</item>
                  <item>4. By ſetting what Price they pleaſe on the Commodities the Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters produce, they having the greateſt Command of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket, there being but one Buyer for them all, and no Nation elſe ſuffered to Trade with them; nor they allowed to ſend their Product any where but to <hi>England.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Now all this as well hinders the Trade for <hi>England,</hi> as it does Injury to the Plantations of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All that this Company pretends to about Charges of Preſents to the Natives of <hi>Guiny,</hi> maintaining of Factories on the Coaſt, Building and Maintaining of Fortifications, and Officers, and Souldiers, can better be performed by a Company regulated, as is already propoſed, than by this.</p>
            <p>But at <hi>Mingo, Alampo, Pittaw,</hi> the two <hi>Papaws, Arda, Quida,</hi> Old and New <hi>Callabar,</hi> and <hi>Angola,</hi> which are the chief Places of Trade for Negroes, the Company have no Forts nor Caſtles, nor are at any charge, and therefore moſt unreaſonable to exact from their Fellow-Subjects 40 <hi>per Cent.</hi> for Trading thither, as they have done, and do.</p>
            <p>This Company takes the ſame Courſe now, as is propoſed the regula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Company ſhould do, but then its to whom they pleaſe, and at ſuch exceſſive Rates, that none can ſuppoſe it is for maintaining their Forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications, but in plain terms a perfect Tax and Impoſition upon the Subjects, that none ſhall go about their lawful Occaſions on the Coaſt of <hi>Guiny,</hi> except they will pay them 20. 25. and ſo to 40. <hi>per Cent.</hi> a Tax greater than ever any King laid upon his own Subjects. So then this Company can have no pretence to a Patent, for they neither are firſt Diſcoverers, nor the prime Traders to this Coaſt, and therefore have no Reaſon to expect the Confirmation of their Patent by an Act of Parliament, to the Deſtruction of the reſt of their Majeſties Subjects.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
